Guide to the Richard H. Jahns Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard H. Jahns papers
circa 1916-1983
SC0306
Jahns, Richard H. (Richard Henry), 1915-1983
61.5 Linear feet
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and articles. The Jahns papers reflect the breadth of his research and teaching interests, from glacial deposits to seismic hazards. Also included are materials related to his public service and consulting activities with NASA, Atomic Energy Commission, the National Science Foundation, the Stanford University Committee on Earthquake Preparedness, University Committee on Land and Building Development, the California State Seismic Commission, and two field notebooks concerning the granite district of Milford, New Hampshire.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Richard Jahns.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of Geology and Applied Sciences and Dean of the School of Earth Sciences at Stanford University, 1965-1983. Jahns came to Stanford following teaching positions at Cal Tech and Penn State, where he also served as Dean of the College of Mineral Industries. Jahns received many national awards and published over 100 monographs. He died in 1983.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and articles. The Jahns papers reflect the breadth of his research and teaching interests, from glacial deposits to seismic hazards. Also included are materials related to his public service and consulting activities with NASA, Atomic Energy Commission, the National Science Foundation, the Stanford University Committee on Earthquake Preparedness, University Committee on Land and Building Development, the California State Seismic Commission, and two field notebooks concerning the granite district of Milford, New Hampshire.
Access Terms
Jahns, Richard H. (Richard Henry), 1915-1983; Stanford University. Department of Geology. Faculty.; Stanford University. School of Earth Sciences. Dean's Office.; Earth Sciences.; Earthquakes.; Geology.; Milford (N. H.).
Collection Contents
- Course and Teaching Materials, Series 1
  Includes correspondence, reports, articles, recommendations, studies, and materials related to the Seismic Safety Commission, the California Academy of Sciences, the Geological Society of America, and the World Petroleum Congress.
  - Course materials on charts and mapping, topics (Box 1)
  - Course materials – handouts, etc., topics (Box 2)
  - Course materials – handouts, topics (Box 3)
  - Course materials (Box 4)
  - Course materials, student papers (Box 5)
  - Course materials – articles (Box 6)
  - Course materials (Box 7)
  - Course materials/personal papers (Box 8)
  - Course materials (Penn State)/miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Files by University/College name (Box 10)
  - Class Grade Books [restricted] (Box 11)
- Office Files, Series 2
  - Southern California Pegmatites and miscellaneous other background studies (Box 1)
  - Seismic Safety Commission; General Earthquake materials (Box 2)
  - California Mining Board (Box 3)
  - Weather, climate, ground (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous files – reports, studies, correspondence (Box 5)
  - Old Engineering Geology reports (Box 6)
  - New England materials (Box 7)
  - Pegmatite materials (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous photographs – topically organized (Box 9)
  - State Mining Board and miscellaneous teaching materials (Box 10)
  - Seismic Safety Commission (Box 11)
  - Seismic Safety Commission / World Petroleum Congress (Box 12)
  - World Petroleum Congress (Box 13)
  - Seismic Safety Commission, 1979-82 (Box 14)
  - Seismic Safety Commission, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Geological Society of America Chron, 1969-72 (Box 16)
  - Geological Society of America Chron, 1972 -, subjects (Box 17)
  - General Correspondence Alpha A-K (Box 18)
  - General Correspondence Alpha L-Z (Box 19)
  - Recommendations [restricted] (Box 20)
  - California Academy of Sciences / California Division of Mines and Geology, U. S. Geological Survey (Box 21)
  - California Academy of Sciences / California Division of Mines and Geology (Box 22)
  - Societies (Box 23)
  - Societies (Box 24)
  - Correspondence Subjects (Box 25)
  - Correspondence Subjects (Box 26)
  - Correspondence Subjects (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Subjects (Box 28)
  - Correspondence Subjects, Chron files (Box 29)
  - Chron files miscellaneous (Box 30)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-1982-262
  - Two field notebooks, 1937, concerning the granite district of Milford, New Hampshire; and 1 reprint (Box 1)